luke two in those days a decree went out from caesar augustus that all the world should be registered this was the first registration when quirinius was governor of syria
and all went to be registered each to his own town and joseph also went up from galilee from the town of nazareth to judea to the city of david which is called bethlehem
because he was of the house and lineage of david to be registered with mary his betrothed who was with child and while they were there the time came for her to give birth
and she gave birth to her firstborn son and wrapped him in swaddling cloths and laid him in a manger
because there was no place for them in the inn and in the same region there were shepherds out in the field keeping watch over their flock by night
and an angel of the lord appeared to them and the glory of the lord shone around them and they were filled with fear and the angel said to them
fear not for behold i bring you good news of great joy that will be for all the people
for unto you is born this day in the city of
david a savior who is christ the lord and this will be a sign for you you will find a baby
wrapped in swaddling cloths and lying in a manger and suddenly there was with the angel a multitude
of the heavenly host praising god and saying glory to god in the highest and on earth peace
among those with whom he is pleased when the angels went away from them into heaven the shepherds
said to one another let us go over to bethlehem and see this thing that has happened which the
lord has made known to us and they went with haste and found mary and joseph and the baby
lying in a manger and when they saw it they made known the saying that had been told them
concerning this child and all who heard it wondered at what the shepherds told them
but mary treasured up all these things pondering them in her heart and the shepherds returned
glorifying and praising god
for all they had heard and seen as it had been told them and at the end of eight days when he
was circumcised he was called jesus the name given by the angel before he was conceived in the womb
and when the time came for their purification according to the law of moses they brought him
up to jerusalem to present him to the lord as it is written in the law of the lord every male who
first opens the womb shall be called holy to the lord and to offer a
sacrifice according to what is said in the law of the lord a pair of turtle doves or two young
pigeons now there was a man in jerusalem whose name was simeon and this man was righteous and
devout waiting for the consolation of israel and the holy spirit was upon him and it had been
revealed to him by the holy spirit that he would not see death before he had seen the lord's christ
and he came in the spirit into the temple and when the parents brought in the child
jesus to do for him according to the custom of the law he took him up in his arms and blessed
god and said lord now you're letting your servant depart in peace according to your word for my eyes
have seen your salvation that you have prepared in the presence of all peoples a light for
revelation to the gentiles and for glory to your people israel and his father and his mother marveled
said about him and simeon blessed them and said to marry his mother behold this child is appointed
for the fall and rising of many in israel and for a sign that is opposed and a sword will pierce
through your own soul also so that thoughts from many hearts may be revealed and there was a
prophetess anna the daughter of funuel of the tribe of asher
she was a virgin and then as a widow until she was eighty-four she did not depart from the temple
worshiping with fasting and prayer night and day and coming up at that very hour she began to give
thanks to god and to speak of him to all who were waiting for the redemption of jerusalem
and when they had performed everything according to the law of the lord they returned into galilee
to their own home and to their own home and to their own home and to their own home and to their
own
are
and when he was twelve years old they went up according to custom and when the feast was ended
as they were returning the boy jesus stayed behind in jerusalem his parents did not know it
but supposing him to be in the group they went a day's journey but then they went to the temple
they began to search for him among their relatives and acquaintances.
And when they did not find him,
they returned to Jerusalem searching for him.
After three days they found him in the temple,
sitting among the teachers,
listening to them and asking them questions.
And all who heard him were amazed
at his understanding and his answers.
And when his parents saw him,
they were astonished.
And his mother said to him,
Son, why have you treated us so?
Behold, your father and I have been searching for you in great distress.
And he said to them,
Why were you looking for me?
Did you not know that I must be in my father's house?
And they did not understand the saying that he spoke to them.
And he went down with them and came to Nazareth
and was submissive to them.
And his mother treasured up all these things in her heart.
And Jesus increased in wisdom and in statutes,
and in favor with God and man.